Finding Aid for Milan Area Historical Society collection, 1833-2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Milan Area Historical Society collection 1833-2008
Milan Area Historical Society.
0426 Bp 2; Bp Outsize; UBPl
9 linear feet in 11 boxes
4 oversize volumes
2 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was deposited by the Milan Area Historical Society (donor no. 9322 ) in various accessions. The bulk of the materials came to the library in 2010.
Periodic additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The Milan Area Historical Society was established to preserve the history of Milan, Michigan and surrounding areas in Washtenaw and Monroe counties. The emphasis of the organization was both to make known the history of the community and to collect and preserve original materials documenting the area. An important spearhead for the group was Warren Hale who wrote a historical column for the Milan Leader and who encouraged citizens to send photographic and other original material to be included in a proposed museum. Pending the establishment of such a museum, many of the materials have been deposited with the Michigan Historical Collections for preservation and access.
The Milan Area Historical Society collection consists of Visual Materials and Collected Historical Materials. The Visual Materials includes postcards and photographs of the Milan area dating from the 1860s to 2006. Also included are photographic negatives of Paul Holcomb who was both a private photographer and photographer for the Milan newspaper. The Collected Historical Materials includes documentation of area businesses, community events, prominent individuals and families, organizational records, high school materials, and newspaper clippings dating to 2008.
Subjects:
Fraternal organizations--Michigan--Milan.; Hack, Bethuel.; Mead family.; Independent Order of Odd Fellows. Wolverine Lodge no. 197 (Milan, Mich.); Milan (Mich.)--Biography.; Milan (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Milan (Mich.)--Commerce.; Milan (Mich.)--History.; Milan (Mich.)--Social life and customs.; Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--Milan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Milan (Mich.); Postcards--Michigan--Milan.; Butchers--Michigan--Milan.; Business enterprises--Michigan--Milan.; Farming--Michigan--Milan.; Dwellings--Michigan--Milan.; Laborers--Michigan--Milan.; Baseball--Michigan--Milan.; Theatrical productions--Michigan--Milan.; Clothing stores--Michigan--Milan.; Parades--Michigan--Milan.; School children--Michigan--Milan.
Contributors: Visual Materials
Holcomb, Paul.
Genre Terms:
CD-ROMs.; Group portraits.; Photographs.; Postcards.
- Milan history presentations
  - Photographs (some with identifications) by Martha Churchill detailing the history and development of downtown Milan 2007, 12 optical disks CD-ROMs (Box 1)
  - Photo indexes, 3 optical disks CD-ROMs (Box 1)
- Visual Materials
  - Milan Postcards
    - Index to images, 1 print-out; 1 optical disks CD-ROMs (Box 1)
    - Businesses (Box 1)
    - Churches (Box 1)
    - Costume Party (Box 1)
    - Crooked Tree (Box 1)
    - Depot, etc. (Box 1)
    - Factories -- Foundries (Box 1)
    - Ford Complex (Box 1)
    - Homes (Box 1)
    - Main Street, East (Box 1)
    - Main Street, West (Box 1)
    - Orchestras (Box 1)
    - River Street (Box 1)
    - Schools (Box 1)
    - Village Hall Firebarn (Box 1)
    - Wabash Street (Box 1)
    - Water -- Sewer Work (Box 1)
    - Water Tower, etc. (Box 1)
    - Wilson Mill (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Earlier images, 1880s-1930s
      (include scattered images dating to 1860s)
      - Business establishments (Box 2)
        - Exteriors, 2 folders (Box 2)
          (see also oversize folder)
        - Interiors, 2 folders (Box 2)
        - Business district/Main Street general (Box 2)
        - Garrick's Movie Theatre/Milan Theatre (Box 2)
      - Dunsmore family (?) (Box 2)
        (in oversize box 10)
        (images include patriotic parade)
        (given to Beverly Smith from her aunt Ola Dunsmore)
      - Events various, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Family groupings, 3 folders (Box 2)
        (include tintypes)
      - Farm life (Box 2)
      - Individuals (Box 2)
      - Laborers, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Milan area (out of town); includes various mills; also Cone, MI (Box 2)
      - Milan Band, ca. 1908 (Box 2)
      - Milan train wrecks (Box 2)
      - Miller Family, about 1897 (Box 2)
      - Parades, outdoor events, bands and other musical groups (Box 2)
        (see also oversize box 10)
      - Patterson Family 1897 (Box 2)
      - Residences (Box 2)
      - School building (Box 2)
        (first brick school, built in 1869, burned in 1900)
      - Schools
        - Azalia School, Dundee, Michigan 1925 (Box 2)
        - First Mead School 1887 (Box 2)
        - Second Mead School (Box 2)
        - Fryberg School (Box 2)
        - Lewis School 1890s (Box 2)
        - Mooreville School (Box 2)
        - Palmer School 1926 (Box 2)
        - Raleighville School (Box 2)
        - Milan Grade School
          - undated 1897 (Box 2)
          - 1906-1927 (Box 2)
          - 1932-1953 (Box 2)
        - Milan High School
          - Athletics -- Boys (Box 3)
          - Athletics -- Girls (Box 3)
          - Class pictures, 5 folders (Box 3)
            (see also oversize box 10 and oversize folder)
          - Graduation Photos (Box 3)
          - School picture, 9th-12th grade 1905 (Box 3)
          - Old Milan School building 1895 and newer building, circa 1940 (Box 3)
          - Drake (Byron) school pictures (Box 3)
      - Sports teams: Ideal Furnace Co. baseball team and other teams; also hunting photos (Box 3)
      - Theatricals -- cast members of local productions on stage, 3 folders (Box 3)
      - Tile yard (Box 3)
      - Tornado "Cyclone" 1920 (Box 3)
      - Veterans and other fraternal organizations, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Wagons, trucks, and other vehicles (Box 3)
      - Wilson family (include tintype and daguerreotype) (Box 3)
      - Women's groups (Box 3)
      - Non-family groupings, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
      - Copy prints of earlier images (Box 3)
      - Tintypes (Box 3)
    - Later images, mainly after 1940
      - American Boiler & Foundry Co., fire 1948 (Box 4)
      - Buildings (snapshots) 1940s-1980s (Box 4)
      - Buildings (snapshots) 1990s (Box 4)
      - Business enterprises -- downtown views (Box 4)
      - Churches (Box 4)
      - Community events (Box 4)
      - Events (Box 4)
      - Girl Scouts, late 1940s-1950s (Box 4)
      - Groups: firemen, businessmen, etc. (Box 4)
      - Immaculate Conception Catholic Church (Box 4)
      - Junior Chamber of Commerce (Box 4)
      - Homes (Box 4)
      - Individuals, some non-family groupings (Box 4)
      - Inland-Scholz groundbreaking 1971 (Box 4)
        (with Governor William Milliken)
      - Klak open house (Box 4)
      - Mead family photos (Box 4)
      - Memorial Day 1950 (Box 4)
      - Mendelsohn Choir 1939-1940 (Box 4)
      - Methodist Church (Box 4)
      - Milan Theater (Box 4)
      - Milan Village presidents (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
      - Old Shack -- tavern (Box 4)
      - Pepper Pontoon Boats (Box 4)
      - Post Office related (Box 4)
      - Railway/Rail station (Box 4)
      - Red Feather Queen 1951 (Box 4)
      - Residences (Box 4)
      - School class pictures; high school athletics (Box 4)
      - Servicemen (portraits of Milan servicemen who served in World War II) (Box 4)
      - Silk family photos (Box 4)
      - Sinkule Motors (Box 4)
      - Teachers (Box 4)
      - Tornado August 1979 (Box 4)
      - Trains (Box 4)
      - Troop family (Box 4)
      - Wilson Park (Box 4)
  - Paul Holcomb collection
    (Paul Holcomb was printer, later photographer for the Milan Leader (1930-1948) and the Ann Arbor News (1948-1975))
    - Negatives 1945-1976 include images taken for Milan newspapers, also private commissions; subjects relate to community events, high school athletics, the Milan Fair, Milan businesses and community groups (Box 5)
      (negative files include occasional prints)
- Collected historical materials
  - Bassitt scrapbook/ photograph album (Box 6)
    (Eli Bassitt was Milan mayor and owner of Bassitt's department store)
  - Birman Motor Sales 1930s (Box 6)
  - Ciesielski, Muriel J. (programs photographs, etc.) (Box 6)
  - Civil War veterans from Milan area (Box 6)
  - Conde, John E., account book 1840s-1850s (Box 6)
  - "Crooked Tree" (information about) (Box 6)
  - Dare Aircraft Company (Box 6)
  - DeTar (Dr. John) (Box 6)
  - Drake (D.D.) and family -- ledgers, letterpress book photographs and photograph album, 1855-1919 (scattered), 2 folders (Box 6)
    (include team photo of the MHS basketball team, 1914)
  - Envotech (hazardous waste dispute) (Box 6)
  - Family information (response to newspaper request from the Milan Area Historical Society for residents to provide genealogical information about their families) (Box 6)
  - Farrington-Moore family (Box 7)
  - Frisbie family (Box 7)
  - Grainger (Thomas) account books 1880s-1890s (Box 7)
  - Gay (Donald) and family (Box 7)
  - Hack House material (Box 7)
  - Hack (Bethuel) family
    - Genealogical information and typescript of letter written to his children April 19, 1836 (Box 7)
    - Letter from Bethuel and Sally Hack to family members 1836 (Folder 1)
    - Letter from Bethuel and Sally Hack to family members 1836 (Folder 2)
      (continued)
  - Hill, Alice Putnam autograph album 1882-1884 (Box 7)
  - Hoffman, Alexander, pocket diaries 1852, 1873 (Box 7)
    (Hoffman was resident of Grand Blanc)
  - Holland family (Box 7)
  - Hooker family (Box 7)
  - Independent Order of Odd Fellows, Wolverine Lodge, no. 197
    - Record book: initiatory work, degree work, financial records 1872-1880 (Volume 1)
    - Minute book 1917-1919 (Volume 2)
    - Minute book 1923-1926 (Volume 3)
  - Insurance Companies, ledger transcriptions
    - Insurance Company of North America, Ledgerbook kept by Mel Barnes, Agent (Box 7)
    - Hartford Fire Insurance Co. Ledger from 1882-1895 (Box 7)
  - Janny, Jacob and Esther Betts marriage record October 11, 1820 (Box 7)
    (include names of wedding guests and names of children born to them)
  - Johnston (Allen) and family -- personal ledgers, record of hours worked, diaries, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Ladies of the Maccabees for Michigan, charter of the Mooreville Hive No. 375 December 10, 1891 (Folder 1)
  - Ladies of the Maccabees for Michigan, charter of the Mooreville Hive No. 375 December 10, 1891 (Folder 2)
  - Mead family history (Folder 1)
  - Mead family history (Folder 2)
  - Mead School register of students 1895 (Folder 1)
  - Mead School register of students 1895 (Folder 2)
  - Michigan Bridget (woman who participated in the Civil War) (Folder 1)
  - Michigan Bridget (woman who participated in the Civil War) (Folder 2)
  - Milan Area Historical Society miscellaneous materials (Folder 1)
  - Milan Area Historical Society miscellaneous materials (Folder 2)
  - Milan businesses advertisements (Box 8)
  - Milan Community Council
    - 1945-1949 (Box 8)
      (also includes material relating to Community Chest campaign)
    - Clippings (Box 8)
  - Milan Fair 1958, 1961-1967, 1969-1978, 1980, 1982 (Box 8)
  - Milan Fourth of July celebration program 1924 (Box 8)
  - Milan High School
    - Class of 1975 yearbook (Box 8)
    - Commencement programs (Box 8)
    - Dedication and Open House 1958 (Box 8)
    - Football and basketball programs 1945-1965 (scattered) (Box 8)
    - Literary Society secretary's book 1887-1888 (Box 8)
    - Reunion (Box 8)
    - School newspaper
      - Milan High Life 1919 (Box 8)
      - Mi-Hi News 1927 (Box 8)
      - Milan High Life 1934 (Box 8)
      - Milan High Life 1935 (Box 8)
      - Milan High Life 1936 (Box 8)
      - Milan High Life 1938 (Box 8)
    - Scrapbook and memorabilia (Box 8)
    - Yearbook 1938 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Milan history -- general (Box 8)
  - Milan Opera House programs (Box 8)
  - Milan Register of Deaths
    - 1907-1912 (Box 8)
    - 1912-1915 (Box 8)
  - Milan school system history (Box 8)
  - Milan Serviceman Committee 1953-1958 (Box 8)
    (thank you letters, clippings)
  - Milan Union Church Society (Box 8)
  - Milan warranty deeds, indentures, etc. (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Materials (Box 8)
  - Monroe County Circuit Court -- lawyer's calendar 1913 (Box 9)
    (probably of E. E. King)
  - Monroe County Country Schools (clippings about) (Box 9)
  - Moores of Mooreville (Box 9)
  - Murray (Robert and Donald), article about (Box 9)
  - Noble family miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Old Fire Barn restoration (Box 9)
  - Osborn (Thelma) scrapbook/album (Box 9)
  - Overholt (Marion) scrapbook of high school activities 1917-1918 (Box 9)
    (include photographs)
  - Peoples Church, Milan (Box 9)
  - Political candidate advertisement cards (Box 9)
  - Post Office and postal miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Putnam, Alice E. autograph album 1879-1882 (Box 9)
  - Reeves family (Box 9)
  - Rendell (Oscar) scrapbook containing obituary notices of Milan residents circa 1900-1950 (Box 9)
  - Rose, La Veta, letters to (Box 9)
  - Sanford, Iva (transcript of diary) 1909-1916 (Box 9)
  - Stebbins family miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Stebbins (Phyllis) scrapbooks, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Stimpson Hotel, possibly of the Knights of Pythias (Folder 1)
  - Stimpson Hotel, possibly of the Knights of Pythias (Folder 2)
    (second copy)
  - Stony Creek, information about (Box 9)
  - Thompson (Hiram), ledger 1830s, photocopy (Box 9)
  - Throop Family (Box 9)
  - Veterans of Foreign Wars, Milan Post 1224, membership cards (Box 9)
    (World War I and later veterans)
  - Weigel family scrapbook containing newspaper obituaries, wedding and anniversary announcements, and memorabilia 1920s-1940s (Volume 4)
  - Wilcox Family, Probate Court Record 1886 (Box 9)
  - Wilson (Thomas), citizenship document 1849 (Box 9)
  - World War I diary (unknown author) (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous and anonymous (Box 9)
    - Diary describing work activities unloading and hauling 1909-1912 (Box 9)
    - Scrapbook of newspaper articles, about 1894-1934 (Box 9)
    - Scrapbook of obituaries of Milan residents, scattered dates, photocopy (Box 9)
    - Scrapbook pages containing obituaries of Milan residents circa 1897-1914, scattered dates (Box 10)
    - Milan Leader (scattered issues of newspaper) (Box 11)
Related Material
The library also has a collection of materials for the Blackmer family. This collection, also received from the Milan Area Historical Society, includes photograph albums (1860s-1930s), daguerreotypes, and a DVD of photographs of members of the David Blackmer and Zeriah Blackmer family of Milan and of the Farmer family of Milan.